Titus Coan Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Titus Coan Family Papers 1806-1923 (bulk 1832-1882)
MSS76760
Coan, Titus, 1801-1882
5,000 items
31 containers
10.3 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Family and general correspondence, diaries, journals, books and writings by Coan on Hawaii, and Coan family material relating mainly to Coan's missionary work in Hawaii, Patagonia, and the Marquesas Islands.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Coan family.; Coan, Fidelia Church, 1810-1872.; Coan, Harriet Fidelia, 1839-1906.; Coan, Lydia Bingham.; Coan, Samuel Latimer, 1846-1887.; Coan, Titus, 1801-1882.; Du Pont, Sophie Madeleine, 1810-1888--Correspondence.; Lyman, Chester Smith, 1814-1890--Correspondence.; Oliphant, Mary--Correspondence.; Oliphant, Sarah--Correspondence.; Robinson, Maria Church.
Subjects
Missions--French Polynesia--Marquesas Islands.; Missions--Hawaii--Hilo.; Missions--Patagonia (Argentina and Chile); Presbyterian Church--Missions.; Religion.; Volcanoes--Hawaii.
Places
Kilauea Volcano (Hawaii)
Occupations
Clergy.; Missionaries.
Provenance
The family papers of Titus Coan, Presbyterian minister and missionary, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sarah Coan Acheson in 1969.
Other Repositories
The New-York Historical Society, New York, N.Y., has a collection of Titus Coan papers and also of his son, Titus Munson Coan (1836-1921). Duplicate and extraneous printed matter deemed inappropriate for retention in the Library's Titus Coan Papers was transferred to the Lyman Museum, Hilo, Hawaii.
Access and Restrictions
The Coan Family Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1801, Feb. 1 Born, Killingworth, Conn.
1819 1826 Taught school in Connecticut
1826 1830 Taught school, Riga, N.Y.
1828 Received into Presbyterian Church, Riga, N.Y.
1831 1933 Attended Auburn Theological Seminary, Auburn, N.Y.
1833 Licensed as a minister by Cayuga County, N.Y. Presbytery Ordained a missionary by American Board of Foreign Missions
1833 1834 Went on missionary expedition to Patagonia
1834 Married Fidelia Church (1810-1872)
1834 Sailed for Hawaii
1834 1882 Missionary, Hilo, Hawaii
1836 Birth of son, Titus Munson Coan (died 1921)
1839 Birth of daughter, Harriet Fidelia Coan (died 1906)
1843 Birth of daughter, Sarah Eliza Coan (died 1916)
1846 Birth of son, Samuel Latimer Coan (died 1887)
1860 and 1867 Made voyages to Marquesas Islands for Hawaiian Missionary Society
1870 1871 Visited the United States
1873 Married Lydia Bingham (died 1915)
1880 Published Adventures in Patagonia. New York; Dodd, Mead
1882 Published Life in Hawaii. New York: A. D. F. Randolph
1882, Dec. 1 Died, Hilo, Hawaii
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Titus Coan family span the period 1806-1923, with the bulk from 1832 to 1882. Consisting mainly of correspondence between members of the families of Titus Coan and his wife, Fidelia Church Coan, these letters document the Coans' lives in Hilo, Hawaii, from 1834 to 1882 and reflect the missionary spirit of that period. The collection organized in five series: Diaries and Journals, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Miscellany, and Printed Matter.
Titus Coan's journals tell of his travels to distant lands in missionary endeavors. In 1833-1834 he recorded a trip to Patagonia to explore the possibility of mission fields in that region. Much of this journal was published in his book Adventures in Patagonia. Journals of two trips to the Marquesas Islands made in 1860 and 1867 describe the land and its inhabitants as well as the progress of missions there, while other journals tell of his journey and early years of residence in Hawaii, where he served for over forty-five years. These experiences were further amplified in his autobiography, Life in Hawaii.
The Coans' correspondence is primarily with family members, including their daughter, Harriet Fidelia Coan, a teacher at Punahou, Hawaii, and their son, Samuel Latimer Coan, who was living in San Francisco in the late 1860s and the 1870s, and describes the day-to-day events of their lives. Other correspondence relating to missionary work is that with Fidelia Coan's sister, Maria Church Robinson, who served with her husband as missionary to Siam from 1834 to 1847, at the same time that the Coans were beginning their service in Hawaii.
The General Correspondence series also reflects the religious feeling and missionary endeavors of the period. The Coans corresponded with other missionaries in the Hawaiian Islands and with friends at home, many of whom were active in societies that supported such work. Correspondents include Sophie Madeleine Du Pont (wife of Admiral Samuel Francis Du Pont), Chester Smith Lyman, Mary Oliphant, and Sara Oliphant.
An extensive collection of printed matter is preserved with the collection. Much of this constitutes, in effect, an article file for Titus Coan consisting of journals to which he contributed. He was particularly interested in volcanoes and wrote many observations on the eruptions of Kilauea, the volcano on the slope of Mauna Loa on the island of Hawaii. These he contributed to the American Journal of Science and Arts. He also contributed extensively to missionary journals such as Missionary Herald and The Friend.
Copies of Titus Coan's two books are included in the Miscellany series along with numerous clippings and articles about him, a copy of Titus Coan; a Memorial (Chicago, Revell [1884] 248 pp.) by his second wife, Lydia Bingham Coan, and some material written in Hawaiian.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
Diaries and Journals, 1818-1881
Family Correspondence, 1818-1916
General Correspondence, 1828-1915
Miscellany, 1832-1957
Printed Matter, 1806-1923
Container List
- Diaries and Journals, 1818-1881 (Box 1)
  Diaries and journals of Titus Coan and his wife, Fidelia Church Coan.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - “Waymarks,” notations of events by Titus Coan, 1818-1881 (Box 1)
  - Patagonian journal, 1833, Aug. 16-1834, May
  - Trip to Hawaii, 1834, Dec. 5-1835, Jan.
  - Journal of Fidelia Church Coan, 1834-1837
  - Early residence in Hawaii
    - 1835, Jan. 6-1839, Apr.10
    - 1840, Aug. 20-1841, Mar. 5
  - Account of baptism of Titus Munson Coan, 1836, Nov. 13
  - Diary of Fidelia Church Coan, 1837-1838, 1841
  - Register of letters by Fidelia Church Coan, 1838-1872
  - Visit to Kilauea, 1855, July 1
  - Trip to Marquesas Islands, 1860, Mar. 17-May 16
  - Voyage to Marquesas Islands, 1867, Apr. 3-June 6
  - Second voyage to the Marquesas Islands, 1867, Apr. 3-May 23
- Family Correspondence, 1818-1916 (Box 2-13)
  Letters received and sent between family members. Arranged alphabetically by writer of letter.
  Typed copies of correspondence between Titus and his wife, Fidelia Church Coan, 1832-1872, are arranged chronologically at the end of the series.
  - Brown, Emma Smith, to Fidelia Church Coan, 1837-1851 (Box 2)
  - Carver, Amanda Church, to Titus and Fidelia Church Coan, 1832-1864
  - Casey, Anna Munson Church Hill, to Titus and Fidelia Church Coan, 1833-1867
  - Church, Barbara and Horace, to Fidelia Church Coan, 1841-1846
  - Church family, miscellaneous correspondence, 1822; 1869
  - Church, Jared O., 1833-1876
  - Church, Samuel Clemon, 1832-1857
  - Clark, Almira Church, 1832-1876; undated
  - Clark, Maria, undated
  - Clark, Samuel, 1838
  - Coan family, miscellaneous correspondence, 1832, 1882
  - Coan, Fidelia Church
    - To Titus Coan, undated
    - To Horace Church, undated
  - Coan, Gaylord, 1818, 1814
  - Coan, George and Mabel, 1831-1834
  - Coan, Harriet Fidelia (Box 3)
    - To parents
      - 1844-1864
      - 1865-1870 (Box 4)
    - To father
      - 1873
      - 1874-1881 (Box 5)
    - To parents, undated and fragments
    - To brothers and nephew, 1856-1905
    - To Samuel L. Coan (brother), 1863-1865; undated
  - Coan, Samuel L.
    - To parents
      - 1849-1865
      - 1866-1872 (Box 6)
    - To Harriet Fidelia Coan (sister)
      - 1854-1871
      - 1872-1875, 1885 (Box 7)
    - To Titus Munson Coan (brother), 1869
    - Miscellaneous
  - Coan, Titus and Fidelia
    - To Harriet Fidelia Coan (daughter)
      - 1844-1855
      - 1856-1864 (Box 8)
    - To Harriet Fidelia Coan (Box 9)
      - 1865-1868
      - 1869-1872, undated (Box 10)
  - Coan, Titus
    - To Harriet Fidelia Coan, 1873-1876
    - To Fidelia Coan, 1866; 1870-1871
    - To Samuel L. Coan (son), 1868-1871
    - To Titus Munson Coan (son), 1855-1872; undated
    - To Connie Ferson (niece), 1864; 1870-1882
    - To William G. Ferson (nephew), 1864; 1870-1882
    - To other family, 1835-1866
  - Coan, Titus or Fidelia (Box 11)
    - To George and Mabel Coan (brother), 1825-1877
    - To George M. Coan (nephew), 1840; 1870-1879
    - To Amanda Church Carver, 1836-1875
    - To Jared O. Church, 1835-1872
    - To Almira Church Clark, 1833-1854
    - To Anna Munson Church Hill Casey, 1835-1848
    - To Samuel Clemon Church, 1832-1837
    - To Maria Church Robinson, 1831-1879
    - To Gaylord Coan (father), 1833-1852
    - To Sylvanus and Heman Coan (brothers), 1834-1835
    - To Elizur Coan (brother), 1832-1846
    - To Mary J. Coan (sister), 1835-1839
    - To Ezra and Fanny Coan, 1835-1862
    - To Fanny Coan, 1863-1882
    - To Lottie Fancher (niece), 1881-1882 (Box 12)
    - To Sally Arnold (sister), 1835
    - To other Church family members, 1835-1859
    - To other Coan family members, 1837-1880
    - Notes and abstracts of letters, 1836–1882
  - Coan, Titus Munson, to mother, 1864
  - Robinson, Maria Church
    - To Titus and Fidelia Coan, 1833-1882; undated
    - To Harriet F. Coan and Titus Munson Coan, 1881; undated
  - Smith-Bagg, Abigail Church, 1864; 1868
  - Waters, Sarah Coan (Box 13)
    - To Harriet Fidelia Coan (sister), 1852-1872
    - To Philip M. Coan, 1916
    - Letters of condolence on death of, 1916
  - Miscellaneous family and unidentified or unknown relationship; fragments
  - Letters of Titus and Fidelia Church Coan
    - Typed copies, 1849-1872
    - Extracts, 1832-1836; undated
- General Correspondence, 1828-1915 (Box 14-16)
  Correspondence with persons other than family members.
  - 1828-1841 (Box 14)
  - 1842-1861 (Box 15)
  - 1862-1915, undated (Box 16)
  - Poems
- Miscellany, 1832-1957 (Box 17-18)
  Clippings about Titus Coan, wills, drafts of writings by members of the Coan family, and pamphlets and copies of books by Titus Coan.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Certificates, passports, and indenture (Box 17)
  - Clippings about Titus Coan and Hawaii
  - Coan, Fidelia Church
    - Drafts of verse
    - Drafts of writings
  - Coan, Harriet Fidelia
    - Death and estate, 1906
    - Miscellany
  - Material in Hawaiian
  - Miscellaneous
    - Lists of letters
    - Manuscripts
    - Notes concerning correspondence
  - Notes on last illness of Titus Coan
  - Pamphlets written by Titus Coan, 1846-1862
  - Pamphlets containing references to Titus Coan, 1818-1957 (Box 18)
  - Speeches not by Titus Coan
  - Titus Coan memorial
  - Titus Coan; A Memorial by Lydia (Bingham Coan)
  - Waters, Sarah Coan, will and estate, 1916
  - Writings of Titus Coan
    - Life in Hawaii
    - Adventures in Patagonia
- Printed Matter, 1806-1923 (Box 19-31)
  - Serial Publications, 1822-1923 (Box 19-26)
    Journals, magazines, and serials publications containing writings of Titus Coan or references to him.
    Arranged by title and therein chronologically.
    - American Journal of Science and Arts (Box 19)
      - 1879, Mar.-1858, Jan.
      - 1858, Nov.-1870, Mar. (Box 20)
      - 1870, May-1880, July (Box 21)
    - Maile Quarterly, 1865, Sept.-1866, Oct.
    - Missionary Herald (Box 22)
      - 1822-1839, Jan.
      - 1840, July-1859, Sept. (Box 23)
      - 1860, May-1885, Feb. (Box 24)
    - Hawaiian Mission Children's Society (Box 25)
      - Annual Reports
        - 1853-1903
        - 1904-1911 (Box 26)
    - The Friend, 1852-1855, 1923
    - Hawaiian Forester and Agriculturist, 1905
  - Books, 1806-1911 (Box 27-31)
    Books relating to missionary work Hawaii and Polynesia, and containing references to Titus Coan and his work in Hawaii.
    Unarranged.
    - Brigham, William T., The Volcanoes of Kilauea and Mauna Loa on the Island of Hawaii (Honolulu, Bishop Museum Press, 1909. 222 pp.) (Box 27)
    - Pickering, William H., Lunar and Hawaiian Physical Features Compared (1906. 179 pp.)
    - Brigham, William T., Notes on the Volcanoes of the Hawaiian Islands (Cambridge, Riverside Press, 1868)
    - Griffin, A. P. C., List of Books Relating to Hawaii (Washington, Govt. Print Off., 1898. 26 pp.)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce and Labor, The International Metric System of Weights and Measures (Washington, Govt. Print. Off., 1906. 15 pp.)
    - A Geography of the Hawaiian Islands (New York, A.S. Barnes, 1889. 26 pp.)
    - The New England Medical Gazette (v.8, no. 2, Feb. 1873)
    - Churchill, William, Beach-La-Mar (Washington, Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1911. 54 pp)
    - Hitchcock, Charles H., Hawaii and Its Volcanoes (Honolulu, Hawaiian Gazette, 1909. 314 pp.)
    - Anderson, Rufus, Foreign Missions (New York, C. Scribner's Sons, 1869. 373 pp.) (Box 28)
    - Wise, Lt., Los Gringos (New York, Baker and Scribner, 1849. 453 pp.)
    - Featherman, A., Social History of the Races of Mankind: Oceano-Melanesians (London, Triibner, 1888. 420 pp.)
    - Cumming, C. F. Gordon, Fire Fountains (London, W. Blackwood, 1883. 2 v.)
    - Bishop, Isabella Bird, Six Months Among the Palm Groves, Coral Reefs, and Volcanoes of the Sandwich Islands (New York, G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1894)
    - Melville, Herman, Omoo (New York, United States Book, 1892. 365 pp.) (Box 29)
    - Bliss, William R., Paradise in the Pacific (New York, Sheldon, 1873. 207 pp.)
    - Hawaiian Mission Children's Society, Jubilee Celebration of the Arrival of the Missionary Reinforcement of 1837 (Honolulu, Daily Bulletin Steam Print, 1887. 204 pp.)
    - Mariner, William, An Account of the Natives of the Tonga Islands in the South Pacific Ocean (Edinburgh, Constable, 1827. 2 v.)
    - Life in Feejee, or Five Years Among the Cannibals, by a lady (Boston, W. Heath, 1851. 423 pp.)
    - Kotzebue, Otto von, A New Voyage Round the World (London, H. Colburn and R. Bentley, 1830. 2 v.)
    - Grant, M. Forsyth, Scenes in Hawaii, or Life in the Sandwich Islands (Toronto, Hart, 1888. 203 pp.)
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis, In the South Seas (New York, C. Scribner's Sons, 1908. 370 pp.)
    - A Memoir of Daniel Wheeler (Philadelphia, Book Association of Friends, 1885. 250 pp.) (Box 30)
    - Tyerman, Daniel, a George Bennet, Journal of Voyages and Travels, compiled by James Montgomery (New York, J. Leavitt, 1832. 3 v.)
    - Anderson, Rufus, History of the Sandwich Islands Mission (Boston, Congregational Pub. Society, 1870. 408 pp.)
    - Anderson, Rufus, The Hawaiian Islands: Their Progress and Condition Under Missionary Labors (Boston, Gould and Lincoln, 1865. 450 pp.)
    - Ellis, William, Narrative of a Tour Through Hawaii (London, H. Fisher, Son, and P. Jackson, 1826. 442 pp.)
    - Memoirs of Marmontel (London, Longman, Hurst, Rees, and Orme, 1806. 4 v.) (Box 31)
    - The Sugar Producing Capacity of the Hawaiian Islands (Judd and Detweiler, Printers, 14 pp.)
    - Ellis, William, Polynesian Researches (Fisher, Son, and P. Jackson, 1831. 4 v.)